Finding Aid for the Dorothy Bethurum Loomis Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Dorothy Bethurum Loomis Papers
undated
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0266
4.05 Linear Feet
Biographical Sketch
Dorothy Bethurum Loomis of Franklin, Tennessee was a Vanderbilt Alumna, Bachelor of Arts 1919 and Master of Arts 1922. She went on to obtain her doctorate from Yale University in 1930 and also studied at Oxford as a Fulbright Fellow. While at Vanderbilt, Loomis was a Founder’s Medalist, editor of the Commodore, president of the Scribblers, vice-president of the YWCA, on the Hustler staff, permanent class secretary, a member of the Kappa Alpha Theta sorority, and Phi Beta Kappa student president. After finishing her education, she taught at Randolph Macon Women’s College and at Lawrence College. In 1937 Loomis was a Guggenheim Fellow in England. By 1940, she accepted a position as Professor of English and head of the department at Connecticut College for Women. In 1946 she served as chairman of the English Institute. Through her professional life Loomis maintained her ties with Vanderbilt University, at times serving as a visiting professor. She was also a member of the Alumni Association Board of Directors, 1953-57. Through her research and dedicated scholarship, Loomis was an authority on the medieval and Anglo-Saxon period.
Scope and Content Note
The Dorothy Bethurum Loomis papers range from material collected at the beginning of the 20th century to those collected in the late 1980s. The first box of the collection consists of Loomis’s biographical and academic materials such as personal correspondences, newspaper clippings, photographs, and handwritten notes found in her papers. Also included are her academic writings/published articles. The next box consists of teaching tools such as handouts, transparencies, and translated works. Boxes 3-5 consist of Loomis’s collected papers relating to the academic scholarship of other Loomis family members, including photographs and articles by her husband Roger Sherman Loomis and his previous two wives, Laura Hibbard Loomis and Gertrude Schoepperle. Boxes 6-9 consist of a collection of articles written by other scholars on medieval studies and the Anglo-Saxon period. The series and subseries of this collection are as follows:
Biographical
Correspondence
Publications
Newspaper clippings
Photographs
Notes
Academic
Articles
Translated Works
Teaching Tools
Loomis family Academics
Roger Sherman Loomis’s Images
Loomis Family Writings
Other Academics’ Writings
- Series I: Biographical
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence: Incoming: from 1920-1957 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence: Incoming: from 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence: Incoming: from 1968-1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence: Incoming: from 1977-1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence: Incoming: undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Publications
    - Metropolitan Museum of Art Bulletin, Summer, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series II: Academic
  - Articles
    - Dorothy Bethurum, “Archbishop Wulfstan’s Commonplace Book,” December, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 18)